Antarctica.（南极洲）
The coldest, the harshest（刺耳的） and the
most remote continent（大洲） on Earth.
No human being has ever descended
Into（走进） the depths that surround it...
..until now.
INDISTINCT（模糊的） RADIO CHATTER
The deep ocean is as challenging to
explore as space.
We know more about the surface of
Mars than we do about the
deepest parts of our seas.
RADIO CHATTER
Now we can dive these uncharted（未知的）
depths to discover
what secrets lie beneath.
INTENSE CREAKING
Sinking down beside the submerged
wall of an iceberg（冰山）,
we enter an unforgiving world.
These waters are
the coldest on Earth.
As we descend into the deep, the
pressure increases relentlessly（残酷的）.
And the light from above
all but disappears.
Yet, incredibly...
..there is life here.
We might have expected that, deep
beneath the surface of
the polar seas, the waters would be
truly barren（贫瘠的）.
But in fact we find life here in
unimaginable abundance.
Nor is such great abundance confined
To（局限于） Antarctic waters.
Currents carry this richness into
the depths of almost every ocean
around the world.
Astonishingly, in the deep sea,
there is more life than anywhere
else on Earth.
The sunlight fades
and the seas darken.
Here in the Pacific,
200 metres down,
we enter an alien world.
The Twilight Zone（阴阳魔界） -
a sea of eternal（永恒的） gloom（阴暗）.
There are strange creatures here.
A pyrosome（火体虫）.
A tube of jelly two metres long that
dwarfs a visitor from above -
an oceanic whitetip shark（白鳍鲨）.
Only a tiny amount of light filters
Down（逐渐扩散） this far.
Survival here means making the most
of every last glimmer（微光）.
A swordfish.
Its eyes are as big as tennis balls,
to help it see
in the perpetual（永久的） dusk.
A squid（乌贼）,
but this is one
that lives only here.
Its right eye looks
permanently downwards.
But its left eye is much bigger and
trained upwards to detect the
Silhouettes（轮廓） of prey（被捕食者）
swimming nearer the surface.
No wonder it's nicknamed
"the cockeyed（斗鸡眼的） squid".
And even stranger.
This is barreleye（桶眼鱼）...
..a fish with a transparent head
filled with jelly（胶状物） so that it can
look up through its skull（脑壳）.
We now know that the Twilight Zone
is a refuge for an incredible
90% of all fish in the ocean.
Only at night do vast shoals（浅滩） of
lanternfish migrate to the surface
to feed on tiny plankton（浮游生物）.
By day, they retreat back down here.
Humboldt squid（美洲大赤鱿）.
Two metres long
and 50 kilos in weight.
Like most squid,
they're voracious（贪婪的） hunters.
There are hundreds of them.
They've found a shoal（鱼群）
of lanternfish,
hiding 800 metres down,
off the coast of South America.
Their tentacles（触手） are armed with
powerful suckers（吸盘）
with which they grab their prey.
And when there are no more
lanternfish to be found...
..they turn on（攻击） each other.
This squid has caught a smaller one
in its tentacles.
To hide its capture（战利品） from the rest,
it releases a smokescreen
of black ink.
But then an even bigger one
challenges it...
..and steals its catch.
The Twilight Zone is the Humboldt
squid's favoured hunting ground.
They seldom go deeper...
..into the world of perpetual
blackness below...
..The Midnight Zone.
Two thirds of a mile from the
surface, beyond the reach the sun.
A giant black void（空间）,
larger than all the rest of the
world's habitats combined.
INDISTINCT RADIO CHATTER
There's life here...
..but not as we know it.
Alien-like creatures produce
Dazzling（眼花缭乱的） displays of light.
Nearly all animals need to attract
mates and repel（击退） predators（捕食者）.
This language of light is so
widespread here that these signals
are probably the commonest
form of communication
on the entire planet.
And yet we still know
little about them.
Hunters illuminate（照亮） themselves,
and by doing so
attract inquisitive（好奇的） prey.
This is fangtooth（狼牙鱼）.
It has the largest teeth for its
size of any fish.
There are pressure sensors all over
its head and body which can detect
anything moving
in the surrounding water.
It's the Midnight Zone's
most voracious（贪婪的） fish.
But prey use light as a distraction.
A decoy（诱饵） of luminous ink（发光油墨）.
Down here, in this blackness...
..creatures live beyond
the normal rules of time.
Siphonophores（无脊椎动物） are virtually（几乎） eternal（永恒的）.
They repeatedly clone themselves...
..some eventually growing longer
than a blue whale.
Down here it snows.
Continuous clouds of organic debris（有机物残体）
Drift（漂流） slowly down from above.
This is food, and a whole variety
of filter feeders（滤食动物） depend on it.
Jellyfish（水母）...
..and delicate sea cucumbers（海参）.
The 1% of marine snow（海洋雪） they miss
eventually settles on the sea floor.
Over millions of years
it forms a layer of mud
up to a mile thick.
It's an empty plain that covers
half the surface of our planet.
The deep sea bed
may at first appear lifeless...
..but it's home to
a unique cast of mud-dwellers.
The sea toad（海蟾蜍）.
It is an ambush（埋伏的） predator
with an enormous mouth...
..and infinite patience.
This fish has been living
for so long here
that its fins have changed
into something more useful.
Feet.
They help it shuffle about（拖着脚走）
on the sea floor.
The flapjack octopus（烙饼章鱼）.
It hovers（徘徊） just above the surface of
the mud as it delicately sifts（筛选）
through it, searching for worms.
But it can jet away at
the first sign of danger.
A sixgill shark（灰六鳃鲨）
as big as a great white（大白鲨）.
It may not have eaten
for an entire year.
It patrols（巡逻） the mud plains
using a minimum amount of energy.
High above, the carcass（尸体） of a huge
sperm whale（抹香鲸） is slowly decaying（腐烂）.
This will be a bonanza（幸运） for the
creatures of the deep.
Food, 30 tonnes of it.
Finally, it settles
on the ocean floor...
..and its presence is soon detected.
Sixgill sharks have an
exceptionally acute sense of smell.
Just 25 minutes after the whale's
carcass arrives...
..a sixgill finds it.
Each bite releases blood
into the current.
The news that food is here
spreads quickly.
Two more ravenous sixgills arrive.
Within 12 hours,
there are seven enormous sharks
Jostling（推撞） with one another as they
compete to tear off mouthfuls.
No-one is prepared to back off.
24 hours later and a third of the
carcass has gone.
The first arrival has gorged（拼命吃） until
it's completely full.
This single meal may be enough to
sustain it for a whole year.
Now the clean-up team arrives.
Spider crabs（蜘蛛蟹） carrying coral（珊瑚虫）
in their hind legs（后肢）,
presumably as makeshift（将就的） body armour.
There are rock crabs（锯缘青蟹） here, too.
They probably detected the carcass
almost as soon as the sharks...
..but they can't move as fast.
A month on, and over 30 species of
Scavenger（食腐动物） are clearing away the last
Edible（可食用的） fragments（碎片）.
But now the scavengers are
attracting their own predators.
Scabbardfish（赞氏叉尾带鱼）,
habitually swimming upright,
are picking them off one by one.
Some of the whale's teeth have been
Dislodged（移位） as the skeleton（骨架） starts to
fall apart.
Four months later, there is nothing
left but a few bones.
But even they are food...
..for something.
Zombie worms（僵尸蠕虫）.
They tunnel into the bones by
injecting acid...
..and so reach the tiny amounts of
fat that still remain there.
It may take decades, but eventually
the last of the bones will crumble（粉碎）
and the whole 30-tonne carcass
will have been recycled.
A whale fall is a temporary oasis（绿洲）
in the desert of the sea floor.
But there are permanent
oases here, too.
Rocks projecting above the mud
provide anchorage（锚地）
for deep-sea corals（深海珊瑚）.
As far down as 3.5 miles,
there are more species of coral
in the deep
than on shallow tropical reefs（热带珊瑚礁）.
Without sunlight,
they rely solely
on food drifting in the current.
And they grow just
a hair's breadth a year.
But some of them can live
for 4,000 years.
They, like their shallow water（浅水）
relatives,
provide homes for
all kinds of other creatures.
Growing among the corals is one of
the most beautiful of sponges（海绵）.
This is Venus' flower basket
（维纳斯花篮：一种偕老同穴属海绵体动物）.
These sponges have lodgers（寄宿者）.
Shrimps.
There are plenty of predators
on the reef（礁石）,
so the shrimps are fortunate.
Both this male and female were swept
into this sponge
when they were tiny larvae（小幼虫）,
along with the minute particles of
food on which the sponge feeds.
They found each other and have been
here ever since.
Now they're full-grown
and the female is carrying eggs.
Once hatched（孵化）, the larvae will swim
out through the sponge's walls.
But the shrimps will never leave.
They can't.
They are now far too big to go out
the way they came in,
and no doubt they will live longer
here than they would
if they were wandering about on the
reef unprotected.
But how one of the simplest of all
animals, a sponge,
is able to build
such a complex structure,
to the great benefit of the
shrimps...
..is a mystery...
..and surely a marvel.
But today their timeless world is
being reduced to rubble（碎块）.
As overfishing empties the
surface waters of the seas,
trawlers have started
to ransack（掠夺） the deep.
Now countless numbers of the reefs
that have flourished（繁荣） here
for millennia（一千年）
lie in ruins.
Over time, organic matter on the sea
floor slowly decays...
..producing methane（沼气）.
In the Gulf of Mexico（墨西哥湾）
these eruptions also release
a super-salty liquid.
Brine（浓盐水）.
Five times heavier than seawater,
it accumulates in great pools
on the sea floor.
It's difficult to make sense
of the sight.
A lake of concentrated（浓缩的） saltwater,
15 metres deep
at the bottom of the sea.
Around its margin（边缘）,
perhaps even more strangely,
there is a profusion（充沛） of life.
Giant mussels（巨人蚌）, that can live and
grow for a century or more,
pack tightly together,
dwarfing the shrimps and squat
lobsters（龙虾） that feed around them.
Cutthroat eels（合鳃鳗）, scavengers,
come to the shores of the brine lake
in search of something edible（可食用的）.
Some even venture into（冒险进入） the brine.
Spending too long in it
can send an eel（鳗鱼） into toxic shock（中毒性休克）.
Its only hope is to rise above it.
It manages to escape.
Others are not so lucky.
The brine embalms（防腐） their bodies...
..and the casualties of decades
accumulate around the margins.
But parts of the deep are
even more hostile（敌对的）.
In places, gigantic cracks（巨大的裂缝） stretch（延伸）
for many miles
across the ocean floor...
..canyons（峡谷） that plunge towards the
centre of the Earth.
Scans from survey vessels（勘探船） make it
possible to graphically reconstruct
an image of this
vast submarine landscape.
The deepest of all,
at almost seven miles,
is the Mariana Trench（马里亚纳海沟）
in the Pacific Ocean.
Even Mount Everest（珠穆朗玛峰）
could disappear inside it.
Down here, in these deep ravines（沟壑）,
it was once thought that nothing
whatever could possibly survive.
But there is life even here...
..a kind of sea slug（海参）.
A so-called "sea pig"（海豚）.
They, and other simple creatures,
manage to survive on the
minuscule amount of food
that drifts down here.
Like this starfish,
they can withstand（抵抗） pressure
equivalent of 50 jumbo jets（大型喷气式客机）
stacked on top of one another.
A remote camera probe（远程摄像探头） reveals
the most extraordinary
discovery of all...
..the ethereal（飘逸的） snailfish（狮子鱼）.
At five miles down,
this is the deepest living fish
so far discovered.
No-one imagined that an animal as
complex as a fish could exist
in such extreme pressures.
From the greatest depths to the
Uppermost（最重要的） limit of
the Twilight Zone, it seems that
there is nowhere in the deep sea
where life of some kind
can't survive.
And we now think that the deep sea
may well be
where life on Earth began.
Here, in a world hidden within
the greatest geological
feature（地质特征） on Earth...
..running right down the middle of
the world's oceans,
an underwater mountain range,
spanning（横跨） the entire globe.
The Mid-Ocean Ridge（大洋中脊）.
In the South Pacific,
the ocean floor is being torn apart.
Over three quarters of the planet's
volcanic activity
occurs in the deep...
..almost all of it along the
Mid-Ocean Ridge.
But from this titanic violence
come great riches.
Gases and scalding（滚烫的） water gush up
through the crevices（裂缝）.
Minerals（矿物） condensing（冷凝） from these jets
build up great chimneys（烟囱）...
hydrothermal vents（深海热泉）.
This one, 30 metres tall,
has been named Godzilla（哥斯拉）.
Astonishingly, we now know
that they hold as much life
as tropical rainforests（热带雨林）.
In places, half a million
individual animals
are crammed into（填满）
a single square metre.
They depend entirely for
their food on bacteria.
And THEY feed on chemicals dissolved
in the searingly hot fluid（炙热的液体）.
Crabs consume the bacterial mats（生物薄膜）
that coat their shells.
Others maintain bacterial cultures
actually within their bodies.
Shrimps carry such cultures
in their mouthparts（口器）,
but that is a strategy
fraught with（充满） danger.
To provide sustenance（食物）
for these microbes
the shrimps must dash
into（冲进） the hot vents...
..and that risks being boiled alive.
In the last decade
the number of hydrothermal vents
discovered has doubled.
Every one has its own unique
character and community.
But perhaps the most important one
of all is in the Atlantic.
It has been named "The Lost City".
Within its 60-metre towers,
something truly extraordinary
is taking place.
Under extremes of pressure and
temperature, hydrocarbons（碳氢化合物） -
the molecules（分子） that are the basic
component of all living things -
are being created spontaneously（自发的）.
Indeed, many scientists now believe
that life on Earth may have begun
around a vent like this,
four billion years ago.
We now know that there are deep seas
on the moons of Jupiter and Saturn.
If life can exist under such
extreme conditions down here,
then surely it could exist
somewhere out there.
The team spent more than 1,000 hours
filming in the deep ocean,
mostly from the research vessel
Alucia and her twin submersibles（潜水器）,
Deep Rover and Nadir.
Their most ambitious mission
was to Antarctica（南极洲）,
hoping to film life
two thirds of a mile down,
something never attempted before.
We honestly do not know what we're
going to find down there.
We're going to a place that has
never been explored.
There could be nothing,
there could be a carpet of life,
there could be anything in between.
Who knows?
It's a huge technical challenge.
The water temperature here can reach
minus 1.8 Centigrade.
INDISTINCT RADIO CHATTER
No-one knows for sure
how the subs will cope
with this extreme environment.
OK. Right, I'm going to soak it up（浸泡）.
OK.
Just half an hour into the very
first dive,
a puddle（泥潭） is forming
on the floor of the sub.
Orla confirms it's seawater.
Yeah, Roger. I'm just try to soak up
this puddle of water,
and then see if any more comes.
They must find the leak
and repair it fast.
Are you going to knock that over
my...? Yeah.
You're at 450 metres in a small
bubble and water's coming in.
That's a half an hour straight shot
back up to the surface.
You're kind of thinking about,
"Are we going to fill up with water?
And if we are, there's no way out!"
Yeah.
The sub pilots are well drilled（训练） for
emergencies.
INDISTINCT RADIO CHATTER
Just pass them over. Yeah.
Ralph quickly finds the flood
and fixes it.
He made it all seem absolutely
ordinary and normal and,
"I've got this covered,
don't you worry,"
and within 20 minutes, he did.
The waters of the Antarctic Sound
are potentially rich
but also treacherous（危险的）.
The Sound is ominously（不吉利的） known as
"Iceberg Alley".
We've got to find a place where we
can get the submarines down and up
safely without any icebergs coming
along and bowling them over.
I've got a feeling it's going to be
a bit like a game of Space Invaders.
A metre cube of ice weighs a tonne.
You start sort of grinding（难以忍受的） that
around the sphere, it's delicate.
It's like a big Faberge egg.
One dive brings them right up to the
underside face of an iceberg.
There are icebergs up there that are
the size of a small car, and
then there are icebergs up there
that are the size of Hyde Park（海德公园）.
Enormous.
Conditions here
can change in an instant.
The captain radios down to the subs.
Yeah, Roger that.
We've currently got a couple of big
icebergs coming down
the channel, and it looks like
they're on a collision course（碰撞航向）.
The impact of two icebergs colliding
overhead is clearly heard.
INTENSE RUMBLE（强烈的轰鸣）
That is ice.
With icebergs colliding above and
the weather turning fast,
the subs are quickly recalled.
Once again
their efforts are thwarted（挫败的）.
Finally, after two weeks,
conditions are just right.
Once again the team attempt their
1,000-metre dive in Iceberg Alley.
An hour after leaving the surface
they close in on their goal.
999.
Control, control.
This is Nadir
on bottom, depth -
one-zero-zero-zero metres.
Roger. Depth - 1,000 metres.
Control out. New record!
First manned sub dive
to 1,000 metres in Antarctica!
At the bottom of the ocean, at the
end of the world,
the amount of life they find is
astonishing.
But they are equally astonished
to find that,
two thirds of a mile from the
surface,
icebergs are still a danger.
Rocks can drop from them
as they melt,
and one lands
right in front of the sub.
I don't think many people who are
diving subs
ever consider big lumps of rock
landing on them.
It's, it's not your normal risk.
If it had hit the sphere（球体）,
there's a good chance it would have
put a nice scratch（抓痕） down it.
If something of ten, 15, 20 tonnes
had hit the sub,
it would completely destroy it.
But over the following dives
the team learns it's these
very drop stones
that enrich the Antarctic
deep sea bed,
creating firm anchor points
for life to thrive（茁壮成长）.
Proof that the only way to fully
Appreciate（欣赏） the complexity and
abundance of life in the deep
is to go there ourselves.
Next time, we travel to bustling（熙熙攘攘的）
coral reefs.
Here, animals must go to
extraordinary lengths
to get ahead of the competition in
these crowded cities.